<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Festum festorum, or, A discourse touching the holy feast of Easter shewing how it may be established for ever / by John Gadbury ...</title>
            <author>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G83</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12416431</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12416431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61670</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42829)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61670)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 277:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Festum festorum, or, A discourse touching the holy feast of Easter shewing how it may be established for ever / by John Gadbury ...</title>
                  <author>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. Thompson for the Company of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 63.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Easter.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61670:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61670:1"/>
            <p>Feſtum Feſtorum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> OR, A DISCOURSE Touching the Holy Feaſt OF EASTER. SHEWING How it may be ESTABLISHED For EVER.</p>
            <p>By JOHN GADBURY, Student in Phyſick and Aſtrology.</p>
            <q>—What Holy <hi>Inſtitution</hi> ſoever Other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Year</hi> have received, <hi>ſome</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> from the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in ſucceeding Ages; We may be ſure that this <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was Inſtituted by the <hi>Divine Authority</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelf. <bibl>Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 223.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> 1686.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>N. Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pſon,</hi> for the Company of Stationers, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>CLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61670:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61670:2"/>
            <head>To My LORD, the LORD HENRY<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> EARL of PETERBOROW, Peer of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> Lord <hi>MORDANT,</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEY, Groom</hi> of the <hi>STOLE</hi> and firſt <hi>Gentleman</hi> of His <hi>Majeſty's</hi> BED-CHAMBER, Lord <hi>High-Steward</hi> to the QUEEN, <hi>Lord-Lieutenant</hi> of the County of <hi>NORTHAMPTON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> One of the Lords of His Majeſty's <hi>Moſt Honourable</hi> PRIVY-COUNCIL and Knight of the moſt <hi>Noble Order</hi> of the GARTER. <hi>Health, Happineſs,</hi> and Length of Days be ever Wiſhed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING attempted a <hi>Task</hi> of as great <hi>Uſe</hi> to the <hi>CHRISTIAN CHURCH,</hi> as of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to perform, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Reformation</hi> of Our <hi>COMMON CALENDAR,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:61670:3"/>a <hi>Right Stating</hi> of the <hi>Holy Feaſt</hi> of <hi>EASTER,</hi> (I hope,) for Ever, I do in all Humility caſt both <hi>my Self,</hi> and <hi>It</hi> at Your <hi>Lordſhips Feet,</hi> Imploring Your <hi>Honours Protection</hi> of both, ſo far only as Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhall judge the <hi>Work,</hi> and <hi>Authour</hi> Deſerving. It is a Subject that hath cauſed more Heats in the <hi>Primitive Times,</hi> than any Other, and not without the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of much <hi>SWEAT</hi> and <hi>BLOOD;</hi> So Zealous were the <hi>Antient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in Contending for the <hi>TRUTH.</hi> This Method Once <hi>Embraced,</hi> as I hope, and am ſure it will the ſooner for <hi>Your Lordſhips Owning,</hi> there will never need any more <hi>Quarrels</hi> or <hi>Contentions</hi> about it.</p>
            <p>You are, <hi>(My Lord,)</hi> One of the <hi>Greateſt Stars</hi> in our <hi>Britiſh Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:61670:3"/>and move in an <hi>ORBE</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> very near unto Royal <hi>PHAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BUS</hi> himſelf. Nay, I muſt, in all <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> beg leave to remember the (<hi>Unthinking</hi> part of the) <hi>World,</hi> That, to your very <hi>Great Honour</hi> now, and <hi>Greater Glory</hi> in Ages to come, <hi>Your Lordſhip</hi> was Once nearly <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips'd</hi> with Him too; Being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to an <hi>Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>onable Travel</hi> in your <hi>Elder years</hi> for the <hi>Security of your Life and Liberty,</hi> when both were boldy <hi>ſtruck <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by the <hi>EXCLU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIONERS</hi> of our late <hi>Perilous Times,</hi> that bid ſo <hi>Fair</hi> for the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inging</hi> of the <hi>GOVERNMENT</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, <hi>(My Lord,)</hi> then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> is the moſt <hi>Fit</hi> of any, (if at leaſt you ſhall judge my
<pb facs="tcp:61670:4"/>Mean, but <hi>Well-meant Pains,</hi> worthy ſo great regard,) to bring this <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial Diſcovery</hi> to the <hi>KINGS</hi> moſt <hi>ROYAL EAR.</hi> The Gogitating HERMES ſometimes makes <hi>MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NARCHS</hi> ſhine as <hi>Gloriouſly,</hi> as the Valiant and Commanding <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors:</hi> And the <hi>Ever Famous</hi> JU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIUS CAESAR derives as <hi>Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> (I will not ſay ſo <hi>Great,</hi>) <hi>an Honour</hi> from his <hi>Correction</hi> of the <hi>CALENDAR,</hi> as from his <hi>Victory</hi> obtain'd in the <hi>Pharſalian Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this my <hi>Minute Attempt</hi> happen to be but <hi>Embraced</hi> by your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> I ſhall then hope to live to ſee MENSIS OCTOBRIS, (in our BRITISH <hi>CALEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAR,</hi> at leaſt,) <hi>Exchanger</hi> its
<pb facs="tcp:61670:4"/>Name, for that more <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious</hi> One, of <hi>MENSIS JACO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BI:</hi> To which <hi>Remarkable Month</hi> your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> hath a more then <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Title,</hi> as being moſt <hi>happily Born</hi> therein, and on a <hi>Day</hi> ſo near the <hi>beſt of KINGS,</hi> and in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> with a <hi>Moſt BLESSED EVANGELIST,</hi> though in <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pardon, <hi>(My Lord,)</hi> I beſeech you, my <hi>Great Confidence,</hi> in preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Think</hi> That any thing I am able to <hi>Write</hi> ſhould be Worthy of your <hi>Lordſhips Notice.</hi> And if <hi>This</hi> my <hi>Humble ESSAY</hi> ſhould fail of a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Approbation,</hi> Let it, however, (with your <hi>Lordſhips Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi>) ſtand me in this ſtead, <hi>viz.</hi> to Tell the <hi>World,</hi> and your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:61670:5"/>how much I am, (according to my <hi>mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>) willing to promote the <hi>Engliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and alſo, in a <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Duty</hi> to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> Record my ſelf, by many Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(My LORD,)</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Meaneſt Servant, And Ever Faithful Honourer, JOHN GADBURY</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61670:5"/>
            <head>Feſtum Feſtorum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> OR, A DISCOURSE Touching the ORIGEN and END Of the HOLY FEAST of EASTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the <hi>Feaſts</hi> belonging to the <hi>Chriſtian Calendar,</hi> we ſhall not incur <hi>Errour,</hi> if we Affirm, That the <hi>Holy Feaſt</hi> of EASTER is the <hi>Chief:</hi> It being as Ancient as our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour's Reſurrection;</hi> In memory where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it was declar'd, and inſtituted to be <hi>kept Holy,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) And, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61670:6"/>virtue thereof, all the SUNDAYS in the <hi>Tear</hi> beſides. It is by the <hi>Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> (as liberally quoted by the late Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Reverend <hi>Biſhop of Durham,</hi>) ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the FEAST of FEASTS, and the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of all <hi>Solemnities.</hi> And, hence it is that the learnedſt <hi>Divines,</hi> (though of <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Opinions,</hi> I muſt not ſay of <hi>Different Churches,</hi> for CHRIST hath but ONE CHURCH on <hi>Earth,</hi>) do therefore with the <hi>Antients</hi> term it, and that very juſtly—
<q>The <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>DAYS,</hi> and <hi>QUEEN</hi> of <hi>FEASTS.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Name</hi> thereof, that is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation made up of a <hi>German,</hi> and an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> word, <hi>viz. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt,</hi> and <hi>Star:</hi> The former of which the <hi>Saxons</hi> brought in uſe among us, <hi>viz. Oeſt</hi> ſignifying ARISING, or the EAST. For that the <hi>Sun,</hi> and all the <hi>Stars</hi> do <hi>Ariſe,</hi> or firſt ſhew themſelves in the EAST. The later, <hi>viz. Star,</hi> alludes to our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> the <hi>Bright,</hi> and MORN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING-STAR, whoſe <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> or <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61670:6"/>from the GRAVE, was perform'd on this <hi>Day,</hi> for the <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Juſtification</hi> of all the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>ADAM,</hi> who claim the <hi>Benefit</hi> thereof by a True and Lively FAITH.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gloſſographer, (Mr. <hi>Blunt</hi>) ſays, That EASTER is ſo named of EO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER, a Goddeſs of the <hi>Old Saxons,</hi> whoſe <hi>Feaſt</hi> they kept in <hi>April. Verſtegan</hi> ſays the ſame; and affirms, moreover, that at this preſent in <hi>Saxony,</hi> this FEAST is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led OSTERN, which comes of OSTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONAET; their, and our <hi>Old Name</hi> of APRIL; in which Month this Glorious <hi>Chriſtian Feaſtival</hi> moſt commonly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens. Howbeit, at ſometimes we know it ſhifts place, according to the <hi>Moon</hi>'s Motion, the <hi>Epact,</hi> &amp;c. on which it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, and ſo may come to fall in MARCH, as in this Year 1687. it does. Indeed this <hi>Sacred Feaſt</hi> of EASTER hath certain <hi>Limits</hi> aſſign'd, which (without an <hi>Alteration</hi> by <hi>Authority</hi>) it can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tranſgreſs,</hi> or <hi>Tranſpaſs;</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61670:7"/>it makes its <hi>Progreſs</hi> or <hi>Perambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> between the 22th. day of MARCH, and the 26th. day of APRIL, according to the <hi>Cycles,</hi> &amp;c. on which it depends; and can therefore never go <hi>below</hi> the FORMER, or aſcend <hi>beyond</hi> the LATER And, becauſe the <hi>Boundaries</hi> of this <hi>Holy Feaſt</hi> are not commonly known, I will here preſent you with a <hi>Table</hi> of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Limits,</hi> (according to the old <hi>Julian Correction</hi>) as I find it in that excellent <hi>Collection</hi> of DEVOTIONS, publiſhed by the late Right Reverend <hi>Biſhop of Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Gold. Num.</cell>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">Eaſter Limit</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>March,</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>April,</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61670:7"/>
            <p>☞ Here you are to obſerve, That <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Sunday</hi> is not in this <hi>Table</hi> ſet down againſt each <hi>Golden Number,</hi> but the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Limit</hi> only. And that it is the <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following the ſaid <hi>Eaſter Limit,</hi> which is always EASTER DAY with us here in <hi>England.</hi> As for Example.</p>
            <p>In this Year 1687. the <hi>Golden Number</hi> is 16. now entring the <hi>Table</hi> under the Title of <hi>Golden Number,</hi> with 16. againſt it toward the right hand, I find <hi>March</hi> 21. which is the <hi>Easter Limit</hi> for this <hi>Year</hi> Now <hi>March</hi> the 21. happens on a <hi>Monday;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Sunday</hi> following, which is <hi>March</hi> the 27th. muſt be EASTER DAY. But if the <hi>Limit</hi> fall on a <hi>Sunday,</hi> it muſt not then be EASTER DAY, but the <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following always. <hi>Et ſic de cateris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to dilucidate this matter a little further; You may pleaſe to obſerve, That the <hi>Golden Number</hi> is the ground of the EASTER LIMIT, with regard had to the <hi>New,</hi> or <hi>Full Moon</hi> happening ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what before, or after the VERNAL
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61670:8"/>EQUINOX. And in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1662. You have this plain and general <hi>Rule</hi> laid down for the conſtant finding of EASTER.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>EASTER DAY</hi> is always the firſt Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day after the first <hi>FULL MOON;</hi> which happens near after the One and Twentieth day of <hi>MARCH.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Where you are to Note, That the <hi>Full Moon</hi> here mention'd, is not the true <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of the <hi>Luminaries</hi> in an <hi>Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> but in an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical ſenſe</hi> only; as it has been expreſs'd in <hi>Common-Prayer-Books</hi> formerly, and is particularly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the MASS-BOOK Printed by <hi>Kingston</hi> and <hi>Sution,</hi> in <hi>Quarto,</hi> at <hi>London, Anno</hi> 1555; which was the ſecond year of <hi>Queen</hi> MARY; the Title whereof is, <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale ad uſum Eccleſia Sarisburienſis.</hi> In which is taught how to find EASTER DAY by <hi>New</hi> or <hi>Full Moons,</hi> with theſe Directions.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61670:8"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Carmina docentia per <hi>Novilunia</hi> invenire <hi>Paſcha.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poſt <hi>regum feſta,</hi> quaere <hi>Novilunia</hi> trina,</l>
                  <l>Poſt <hi>Dominica</hi> tertia, <hi>Paſcha</hi> ſacrum Celebra.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aliud.</hi> Poſt veris <hi>Aequinoctium</hi> quaere <hi>Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ilunium</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Et <hi>Dominica</hi> proxima ſacrum celebra <hi>Paſcha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Non verius inveniens, ſi mille legas codices.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>New Moon,</hi> (I ſay) here meant, is not the true <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ptica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Conjunction of the SUN and MOON, but the <hi>Day</hi> only of the MOON's Mean Conjunction, as it was above 1300 years ago, and is in that <hi>Book</hi> found meerly by taking the <hi>Day</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which the propoſed <hi>Year</hi>'s GOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEN NUMBER ſtands in the <hi>Margin</hi> of each <hi>Month.</hi> For the <hi>Calculator</hi> of that CALENDAR knew well enough that That day would be <hi>four Days</hi> after the NEW MOON of his own time, agreeable to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>firſt appearance</hi> of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61670:9"/>MOON, and therefore directs us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the <hi>Day</hi> ſo found, and to tell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a <hi>Syllable</hi> to each <hi>Day,</hi> ſaying, <hi>In Caelis eſt hic;</hi> which if you do, the Syllable <hi>hic,</hi> will fall <hi>four Days</hi> above your GOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEN-NUMBER, and there ſhew you the <hi>Day</hi> of NEW MOON for your time.</p>
            <p>The FULL MOON meant in thoſe <hi>Verſes</hi> are not ſo much as <hi>preciſe Day</hi> of the <hi>mean Oppoſition</hi> of the SUN and MOON, but are to be found in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. To the <hi>Day</hi> of that <hi>Antient</hi> NEW MOON found by the GOLDEN-NUM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BER. add 13. ſo have you the 14th. day of that Eccleſiaſtick CYCLIC Month. For, the GOLDEN-NUMBER of any year ſet to ſome <hi>Day,</hi> between <hi>March</hi> the 7th. and <hi>April</hi> the 6th. declares that <hi>Day</hi> to be the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical beginning of the year.</hi> And the grounds of this CYCLE are theſe, —<hi>March</hi> the 21ſt. was accounted the <hi>Day</hi> of the VERNAL AEQUINOX, (as yet it is with thoſe that follow the ROMAN CORRECTION.) Now if this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61670:9"/>(<hi>viz. March</hi> 8. the day ſucceeding the Boundary, <hi>March</hi> 7.) be the Earlieſt NEW MOON that can be admitted for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Month,</hi> or the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> year:</hi> The next years FIRST MONTH will begin with <hi>March</hi> 27. And the Third years FIRST MONTH will begin <hi>March</hi> 16. The Fourth years FIRST MONTH on <hi>April</hi> the 4th. and ſo in order, as is here ſet down.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                     <cell>Apr.</cell>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.27.16.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>23.12.31.</cell>
                     <cell>20.9.</cell>
                     <cell>28.17.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Apr.</cell>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                     <cell>Apr.</cell>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                     <cell>March.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>25.14.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>22. 11.</cell>
                     <cell>30. 19.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>And then <hi>March</hi> the 8th. again, as at the firſt. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> returning after 19. years very nearly to the ſame place again, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had been taught long before they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and as <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy</hi> alſo at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> demonſtrates.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not here trouble my ſelf to tell you why theſe 19. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61670:10"/>of the FIRST MONTH were not (always) reckon'd in this order: For then I muſt alſo undertake to ſhew you how the CALENDARS in <hi>Miſſals</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer-Books</hi> were <hi>made;</hi> and likewiſe how they came to <hi>differ.</hi> (A great unhappineſs ſure, to all that love Unity!) But this is certain, that the CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENDAR in our <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> in the Edition of 1662. hath its RED NUM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERS reſtored to it; (in which there is no harm,) and the true Eccleſiaſtical NEW and FULL MOONS, with their aſſiſtance, are truly ſtated, as in this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Table.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Aur. Num.—16.5.13.</cell>
                     <cell>2.10.18.7.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>N. Moon. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.9.11.</cell>
                     <cell>12.14.16.17.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>F. Moon. <hi>Mar.</hi> 21.22.24.</cell>
                     <cell>25.27.29.30.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Aur. Num. 15.4.12.1.</cell>
                     <cell>9.17.6.14.</cell>
                     <cell>3.11.19.8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 19.20.22.23.</cell>
                     <cell>25.27.28.30.</cell>
                     <cell>31.2.4.5.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>April.</hi> 1.2.4.5.</cell>
                     <cell>7.9.10.12.</cell>
                     <cell>13.15.17.18</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61670:10"/>
            <p>And thus we have explain'd unto you the 19. EASTER LIMITS, according to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical appointment:</hi> Which many not knowing, are apt to quarrel with <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> about the right timing of this HOLY FEAST in their <hi>Almanacks.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Boundaries</hi> of EASTER, even as the 26th. of <hi>November</hi> is LIMIT of AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENT; upon which day <hi>Saviour-Sunday</hi> never falls, but as ſoon after as may be. And EASTER you ſee hath every year a different LIMIT; upon which this FEAST is not to be celebrated, though it ſhould fall on a SUNDAY, but upon the next SUNDAY following. Unleſs Men will wilfully oppoſe the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which <hi>Authority</hi> hath made, (as ſome conceited perſons ambitiouſly do,) which is not only <hi>unſafe,</hi> but very <hi>hold</hi> and <hi>temerarious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, here we may further <hi>Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> That theſe LIMITS do not oppoſe thoſe ſet down by the late mention'd Renowned PRELATE, but are the ſame with His,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61670:11"/>in reſpect of the FULL MOON; but in regard of the NEW MOON, much lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as any one but meanly skill'd in <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> may by Inſpection perceive.</p>
            <p>The beforeſaid Right Reverend BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHOP. according to theſe LIMITS, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ASTERTABLE for 80. years, beginning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and Printed it with his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> But becauſe it is the ſame with my EASTER TABLE, ſupputated for Two Hundred and odd years, (in reſpect at leaſt of the <hi>Time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>red,)</hi> I forbear Re-printing thereof, and ſhall here preſent you with an <hi>abſtract</hi> of my own <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61670:11"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>An EASTER TABLE accommodated to the <hi>Julia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Gregorian</hi> Accounts for 204 years, beginning <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1677.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Anno Chri.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Julian</hi> Account.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Gregorian</hi> Account.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1677</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1678</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1679</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1680</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1681</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1682</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1683</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1684</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1685</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1686</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1687</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1688</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1689</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1690</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1691</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1692</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1693</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1694</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1695</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1696</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1697</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1698</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1699</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1700</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1701</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1702</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1703</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1704</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1705</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1706</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1707</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1708</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1709</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1710</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1711</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1712</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1713</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1714</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1715</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1716</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1717</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1718</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1719</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1720</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1721</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1722</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1723</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1724</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1725</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1726</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1727</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1728</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1729</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1730</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1731</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1732</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1733</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1734</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1735</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1736</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61670:12"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1737</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1738</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1739</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1740</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1741</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1742</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1743</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1744</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1745</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1746</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1747</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1748</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1749</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1750</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1751</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1752</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1753</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1754</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1755</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1756</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1757</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1758</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1759</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1760</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1761</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1762</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1763</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1764</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1765</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1766</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1767</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1768</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1769</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1770</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1771</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1772</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1773</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1774</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 26</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1775</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1776</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1777</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1778</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1779</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1780</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1781</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1782</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1783</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1784</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1785</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1786</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1787</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1788</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1789</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1790</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1791</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1792</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1793</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1794</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1795</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1796</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1797</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1798</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1799</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1800</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1801</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1802</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1803</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1804</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1805</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1806</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1807</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1808</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1809</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1810</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:61670:12"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1811</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1812</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1813</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1814</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1815</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1816</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1817</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1818</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1819</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1820</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1821</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1822</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1823</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1824</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1825</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1826</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1827</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1828</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1829</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1830</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1831</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1832</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1833</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1834</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1835</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1836</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1837</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1838</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1839</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1840</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1841</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1842</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1843</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1844</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1845</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1846</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1847</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1848</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1849</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1850</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1851</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1852</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1153</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1854</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1855</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1856</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1857</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1858</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1859</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1860</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1861</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1862</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1863</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1864</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1865</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1866</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1867</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1868</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1869</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1870</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1871</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1872</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1873</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1874</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1875</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1876</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1877</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1878</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1879</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1880</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61670:13"/>
            <p>This Table needeth no Explanation; we will therefore proceed in our Diſcourſe of this <hi>Holy Feaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> And that we may be the more plainly underſtood, let it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that there are <hi>Three kinds</hi> of EASTER, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The PASC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or the Jewiſh EASTER.</item>
               <item>The PASC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (I wiſh it were ſo) or our CASTER.</item>
               <item>The PASC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> CASTER.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Jewiſh Eaſter;</hi> which was called the PASSOVER (as ſome obſerve) from the Hebrew word <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ach,</hi> which ſignifies to <hi>Leap,</hi> or to <hi>Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> [As our EASTER doth <hi>Leap,</hi> or <hi>Paſs</hi> from one <hi>Week, Month</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to another, every year.] And it was inſtituted, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no Mundi</hi> 2447. and ordained to be Celebrated from the 15th. day of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Month</hi> called ABIB, (or <hi>March</hi>) to the 21ſt. day of the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive. <hi>i. e.</hi> for VII. days together. Yet ſo, as that the 15th. day, and 21ſt. day were held <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sacred</hi> then the reſt.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61670:13"/>
            <p>We may take notice, That ABIB, or <hi>March</hi> is juſtly called the <hi>Firſt Month</hi> of the <hi>Year,</hi> by reaſon of the VERNAL EQUINOX its falling therein: In Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour whereof, (the <hi>Year</hi> at that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Renewed</hi> unto us, and <hi>Nature</hi> preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us with a new delightful <hi>Spring,</hi>) KINGS formerly were uſed to <hi>date</hi> their REIGNS thence, as this Holy PASCHAL FEAST took its beginning: Whence one wittily writes—</p>
            <q>
               <l>Of <hi>Months,</hi> and of <hi>New Fruits</hi> is <hi>ABIB</hi> Father,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings Reigns</hi> were <hi>Reckon'd</hi> thence, and <hi>Feaſts</hi> together.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The VII. Days were alſo called the <hi>Feast of Azymes; viz.</hi> A time in which it was not <hi>Lawful</hi> to eat <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleavened Bread;</hi> and the <hi>Firſt</hi> of the <hi>Paſcha,</hi> or EASTER, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the PASCHAL LAMB was <hi>Slain,</hi> and <hi>Eaten,</hi> as a Type of our <hi>Ever Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61670:14"/>Paſſion and Reſurrection:</hi> Who, as he was the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> from the Beginning of the World for <hi>Salvation</hi> to all the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>ADAM,</hi> ſo he took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>World,</hi> from all thoſe that truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on him. But the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> having thus appear'd to us, we muſt not JU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ZE, and ſtill reſt in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(i e.)</hi> we ought no longer to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the <hi>Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver</hi> after the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>line.</p>
            <p>I remember to have read ſomewhere of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (I think 'twas S. <hi>Ignatius</hi>) who ſays, <hi>He that keeps</hi> EASTER <hi>after the manner of the</hi> JEWS, <hi>is a Companion of them that</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>our</hi> SAVIOOR. But the ſaying ſeems ſomewhat too ſtrict, at leaſt in my Opinion; ſince to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at all, is a <hi>Duty</hi> of RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GION, and beſpeaks a Veneration to the Memory of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (whether in <hi>Type,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) in ſuch as obſerve it <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> though they do not Celebrate it as they ought: 'Tis the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Buſineſs</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61670:14"/>of RELIGION to enjoyn, and practice the keeping thereof; but 'tis a MATH<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATICAL, <hi>performanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to appoint the right <hi>Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of its Obſervation.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (for ſo it was, and ſometimes, (yet but ſometimes,) is ſtill ſo,) or That EASTER, which we obſerve, (if we believe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) was firſt ordained 322. years <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum,</hi> or after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> SAVIOUR. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Great,</hi> that God-like Chriſtian Emperor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, (who, as Hiſtory informs us) had ſo great an Honour for the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Crucify'd Lord</hi> that on <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> he aroſe, and <hi>beſtowed</hi> the richeſt <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> all over his EMPIRE And from His Example, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were wont to <hi>Releaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> all PRISONE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on this day, excepting ſuch as were <hi>Gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or ſome other very H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> And in the purer times of Chriſtianity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIANS were conſtantly accuſtomed joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61670:15"/>to <hi>Greet</hi> each other, with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Chriſt is riſen.</hi> And the uſual Reſponſe was, <hi>Chriſt is riſen indeed.</hi> Nay, thoſe that were <hi>Enemies</hi> at this time, were <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled</hi> by the only <hi>Pious Amulet</hi> of a <hi>Surrexit Chriſtus,</hi> and ſo became <hi>Friends</hi> again. Oh! that ſo Divine and Heavenly a Practice were Reviv'd among us! This <hi>Noble Emperour,</hi> I ſay, taking notice of <hi>divers Errours,</hi> and Contentions which conſtantly happen'd among <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the days of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> about the <hi>Celebrating</hi> of this HOLY FEAST of our <hi>Saviour's Riſing from the Grave;</hi> Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled from all <hi>Nations</hi> 318 <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and other <hi>Learned Perſons,</hi> as well <hi>Greeks,</hi> as <hi>Latines,</hi> and <hi>Aegrptians;</hi> ſuch as could withal well determine of the <hi>Motions</hi> of the <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> upon which this HOLY FEAST depends: Among whom, EUSEBIUS Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> was chief; He being a moſt <hi>Excellent Aſtronomer,</hi> and <hi>Mathematician.</hi> And he kept them together near <hi>two years</hi> at his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Coſts and Charges.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:61670:15"/>
            <p>And lo! in the year 323. they Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a NEW GOLDEN-NUMBER, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from that in uſe among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> by which <hi>New Number</hi> or <hi>Cycle,</hi> this FEAST was appointed to be <hi>Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> not preciſely upon the firſt FULL MOON of the FIRST MONTH, (as before you heard) or after the VERNAL AEQUINOX, leſt the World ſhould thereby be taught to <hi>Judaine,</hi> afreſh, (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> well obſerves) but, <hi>statim poſt</hi> preſently after, <hi>viz.</hi> upon the <hi>Sunday</hi> next following the firſt FULL MOON, that ſhould happen after the VERNAL AEQUINOX. <hi>Terminis Paſchalis (inquit</hi> Scaliger) <hi>eſt quarta decima Luna menſis, Paſchalis Chriſtianiſeculo</hi> Conſtantini <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Inſtitution of EASTER, as if begun under a <hi>Moveable Horoſcope,</hi> (to ſpeak like an <hi>Aſtrologer.</hi>) was not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued above Seven years after the great <hi>Council of Nice.</hi> For <hi>Anno</hi> 330. <hi>poſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum,</hi> there aroſe many <hi>Differences</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61670:16"/>the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> about it: Which <hi>Controverſie</hi> growing unto ſo great an <hi>height,</hi> and ſo many difficulties ſtarted therein; (Good ASTRONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERS ſure were very ſcarce in thoſe Days) that it continued near 200 <hi>Years</hi> before it could admit of any <hi>Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian:</hi> To the great <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ef</hi> and <hi>Trouble</hi> of CHRISTIANS, and <hi>Scandal</hi> of CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>LAN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>TY.</p>
            <p>But at length, for the quieting of all Contentions about this SACRED FEAST, in the time of JUSTINIAN the <hi>Emperor, viz.</hi> 527. there aroſe one DIONYSIUS ABBAS, a Noble <hi>Roman,</hi> (and one cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by God,</hi> for ſo good and glorious a WORK!) And he taking into conſideration the many ERRORS broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about this HOLY FEAST, began to frame Tables of EASTER, according to the mind of the <hi>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Council;</hi> which he compleated <hi>Anno</hi> 532, poſt <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</hi> And ſo happy and fortunate was the Noble <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in this his performance, That,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61670:16"/>the great <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>CHALCEDON</hi> being ſatisfied with the Truth and Excellency thereof, were pleaſed not only to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, and own it, but alſo to Enact, <hi>That whoſoever held any other</hi> EAS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>than tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> Rome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt as an <hi>HE RETICK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I proceed any further, I conceive it requiſite, for the ſatisfaction of thoſe that are unacquainted with the <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of this SACRED FEAST; and of the many <hi>Troubles</hi> that have invaded the <hi>World,</hi> by reaſon of its not being truly Obſerved, or Celebrated, to tranſcribe a <hi>few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> from the Learned Dr. <hi>CAVE,</hi> in his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> concerning this matter, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Of all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> EASTER chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges the <hi>precedence,</hi> both for its <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> and the great <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> about it; that in, and from the very times of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61670:17"/>APOSTLES (beſides the weekly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi>) there has been always an <hi>Anniverſary Feſtival</hi> in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of CHRIST's RESURRECTION, no Man can doubt that has any inſight into the <hi>Affairs</hi> of the ANTIENT CHURCH. All the <hi>diſpute</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>particular time</hi> when it was to be kept; which became a matter of as famous a <hi>Controverſie,</hi> as any that in thoſe <hi>Ages</hi> exerciſed the <hi>Chriſtian World.</hi> The ſtate of the Caſe was briefly this: The <hi>Churches of Aſia</hi> the Leſs kept their EA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER upon the ſame day whereon the <hi>Jews</hi> Celebrated their PASSOVER, <hi>viz.</hi> upon the Fourteenth Day of the Firſt Month (which always began with the <hi>appearance</hi> of the MOON,) moſtly anſwering to our <hi>March;</hi> and this they did upon what Day of the Week ſoever it fell, and hence were ſtiled <hi>Quart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Decimans,</hi> becauſe keeping EASTER <hi>Quarto decima Lunae,</hi> upon the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Day after the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Appearance</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61670:17"/>of the. MOON The other <hi>Churches</hi> and eſpecially thoſe of the WES<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did not follow this Cuſtom, but kept <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER</hi> upon the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> following the Day of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the more to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and partly to diſtinguiſh between <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> The <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> pleaded for themſelves the <hi>pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Biſhop of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nyrna,</hi> who had liv'd and convers'd with them, having kept it upon that Day, together with St. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the <hi>reſt</hi> of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (who himſelf knew <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and doubtleſs had it from his own mouth,) ſpeaks in a Letter about this very thing, though himſelf was on the other ſide. And POL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>CRATES in a Letter to the ſame purpoſe, inſtances, not only in St. JOHN, but St. PHILL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who himſelf, and his whole <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> uſed to keep it, from whom it had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd down in a conſtant and un-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61670:18"/>
                  <hi>Obſervance</hi> through all the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> of thoſe places, ſome whereof he there Enumerates; and tells us, That <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of that place in a <hi>cunſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had been his Kinſmen, and himſelf the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and that it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been kept by them upon any other Day: This we are not ſo to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, as if St. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had Inſtituted this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Commanded it to be obſerved on that Day, but rather that they did it by way of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> accommodating their Practice in a matter Indifferent to the humour of the AEWIS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> CONVERTS, (whoſe number in thoſe Parts was very great) as they had done before in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Caſes, and particularly in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Saturday,</hi> The <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Churches</hi> alſo, (ſays <hi>Euſebius,</hi>) had for their Patronage an APOSTOLICAL TRADITION or at leaſt pretended it; and were the much more Numerous Party. This <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was the <hi>Spring</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61670:18"/>of great <hi>Bluſhern</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> for the <hi>Biſhops of Rome</hi> ſtickled hard to impoſe their <hi>Cuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> upon the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> whereupon <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> comes over to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to confer with <hi>AN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>CET<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>S</hi> who was then <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> about it; And though they could not agree the matter, yet they parted fairly. After this <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> renew'd the <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,</hi> and was ſo fierce and peremptory in the Caſe, that he either actually did, or ſeverely threaten'd to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the EASTERN CHURCHES, for ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out againſt it. This <hi>Rath,</hi> and <hi>Bold attempt,</hi> was ill reſented by the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Moderate Men of his own Party, who writ to him about it; and particularly <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (a Man, as <hi>Euſebi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> notes, truly anſwering his <hi>Name,</hi> both in his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and his <hi>Life,</hi> QUIET <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>EAC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ABLE,) who grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproved him for <hi>Renting</hi> the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the CHURCH and troubling ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for obſerving the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61670:19"/>
                  <hi>Cuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ms</hi> derived to them from their ANCESTORS; with much more to the ſame purpoſe. But the ASIAN BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> little regarded what was either ſaid, or done at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and ſtill went on in their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> though by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Practices of the other Party, they loſt ground; but yet ſtill made ſhift to keep the Cauſe on Foot, till the coming of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who finding this <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> amongſt others, much to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the CHURCH, did for this, and ſome other <hi>Reaſons,</hi> Summon the <hi>Great Council</hi> of <hi>NICE;</hi> by whom this Queſtion was ſolemnly determin'd, and EASTER ordain'd to be <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> upon One, and the ſame Day throughout the World, not according to the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the JEWS, but upon the LORD<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>DAY, and this <hi>Decree</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd and Publiſh'd by the <hi>Imperial Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> Thus far this Learned Author, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Part 1. cap. 7. pag. 185. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61670:19"/>
            <p>To add one <hi>Teſtimony</hi> further in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this <hi>Argument,</hi> I find in a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> lately Printed by <hi>N. Thompſon,</hi> Entitled, <hi>The State of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch-Affairs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> under the</hi> Romans, <hi>and</hi> Britiſh <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> viz.
<q rend="margQuotes">—In this Council (of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>) was further Order made, for the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Obſervation of</hi> EASTER, upon the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> following the 14th. Day of the firſt MO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>N after the VERNAL AEQUINON: For the better finding out of which, it was recommended to the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> every year to give notice to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon what Day EASTER was to be obſerved; and this was to be communicated unto all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> MOTER <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And during MASS on the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with a loud Voice, declar'd the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing EASTER, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>NT and all other <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> were regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And accordingly the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> alſo were guided, until <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61670:20"/>
                  <hi>ROME</hi> was interrupted by <hi>Domeſtick Brails,</hi> and the Invaſion of the <hi>SAXONS.</hi> And when by ſuch interruption the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans</hi> vary'd from the <hi>Weſtern Churches,</hi> they kept not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ASTER as the <hi>Quarto Deci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> preciſely upon the 14th. Day of the MOON after the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> mode: But if that 14th. Day happen'd upon a <hi>Sunday,</hi> they did not defer the <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> until the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nday</hi> following, as other <hi>Catholick Chriſtian</hi> CHURCHES uſed to do.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Little Quot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> would bear a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which I could willingly afford to it, did not I <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at <hi>Conciſeneſs.</hi> But I refer you to the Book it ſelf, which is worth your peruſal.</p>
            <p n="3">III. To re-aſſume our former matter: The <hi>Correction</hi> by DIONYSIUS ABBAS, by virtue of the Decree of the <hi>Council,</hi> not of <hi>VICE,</hi> (though that led to this,) but of <hi>CHALCED<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> (as I mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) continued about 1050. years, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61670:20"/>ſo much as being once queſtion'd, <hi>viz.</hi> unto the year 1582. No Man until that time ever daring to preſume to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>Celebration</hi> of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>But then, <hi>viz. Anno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> being ſo eminently obvious in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of its Celebration, (ſo hard and difficult a matter it is for Time and Truth long to keep company together.) The <hi>word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and worthy minded <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the XIII. was (by ſome Divine Impulſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly) moſt happily moved to a <hi>Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to be framed; which after his Name, and in Memory of ſo excellent a Service to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was call'd the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> For it was moſt apparently ſeen that the <hi>Aequinones</hi> fled Backward, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>March</hi> the 21st. day, unto <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the 11th. day, no leſs than Ten Days in time. (A great Errour! and was moſt fit to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.) By reaſon of which <hi>Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> there happen'd two FULL MOONS
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61670:21"/>after the <hi>Vernal Aequinow,</hi> before EASTER could be Celebrated: And conſequently there would be TWO EASTERS in One Year; or within the Compaſs of 365 Days; as it ſtill very often happens with us in <hi>England,</hi> and in other Places, where ever the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is uſed, for want of a due Correction.</p>
            <p>The obſervation of which <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an.</hi> (I ſay) occaſion'd the good <hi>POPE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to alter the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which he did by ſubſtracting <hi>Ten Day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> from the <hi>Family Tray</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to the <hi>Fifteenth Day</hi> thereof, Incluſive, <hi>Anno</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>82. for prevention of ſo remarkable an Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience as the common <hi>EASTERTA. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ES</hi> were chargeable withal. Which <hi>Anticipa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>un</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, in proceſs of time, Our BLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and St. <hi>JOHN</hi> BA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, (as the skilful in Aſtronomy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,) muſt come to exchange their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>RTST's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fall in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> when the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:61670:21"/>is in <hi>Cancer;</hi> and that of the BAPTIST, in <hi>December,</hi> when the <hi>Sun</hi> is in <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn.</hi> An ERROUR which greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved the then <hi>Chriſtian Authority</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a correction of.</p>
            <p>And for prevention of this <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (an offence even againſt the <hi>Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as charging the orderly motions of the STARS with diſorder,) the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church</hi> have Reform'd their CA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAR, and PASCHAL TABLES to ſuch a degree of <hi>certainty,</hi> that they always produce <hi>their</hi> EASTER on the SUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAY following the firſt FULLMOON <hi>post Aequinoctium Vernalem:</hi> Nearly (not fully,) agreeable to the <hi>Decree</hi> of the COUNCIL of <hi>NICE</hi> Unto which, the Rule for finding EASTER even in our <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> conſents, though the TABLE of this HOLY FEAST therein be very often contrary thereunto. As indeed to our ſhame it muſt, until we ſhall be ſo happy as to obtain a COR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RECTION of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAR,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61670:22"/>by which our great FESTIVAL is at preſent governed.</p>
            <p>But, what then? Is the emendation of POPE <hi>GREGORY</hi> exactly true? It were indeed to be wiſhed ſo, but we know it falls ſhort of <hi>Verity,</hi> though not ſo much as the JULIAN ACCOUNT: Yes, and calls alſo for a CORRECTION, though not ſo <hi>loudly</hi> and <hi>ſtrongly.</hi> It is a <hi>Younger Establiſhment,</hi> and therefore more <hi>vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> and <hi>ſimilar</hi> to TRUTH. Whereas ours is as <hi>Antien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as the good <hi>DIONY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>I<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S EXIG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and with <hi>Age</hi> grown very <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>decrepid,</hi> humbly imploring AUTHORITY to conſider its caſe, and yield it ſuch relief, and ſupport, as to their <hi>Wiſdoms</hi> ſhall ſeem moſt fit and convenient.</p>
            <p>But although the <hi>Gregorian Account</hi> be not ſo compleat and perfect as may be wiſhed, I will yet acknowledge (with Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and others,) that it is much more <hi>Correct</hi> and <hi>Certain</hi> than the <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>AN.</hi> And that in ſeveral regards:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61670:22"/>Firſt, (as he well obſerves,) the Quantity of the <hi>Gregorian Year</hi> doth better accord to the <hi>Heavenly Motions.</hi> Secondly, for that the AEQUINOXES and SOLSTICES are thereby more firmly bound to certain Days. And Thirdly, becauſe EASTER is (generally) more truly Celebrated, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mind of the <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>NICENE</hi> COUNCIL.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs we may complain, (with <hi>Clavius,</hi>) That the <hi>Solar year</hi> it ſelf is not exactly determin'd: The exact motion of the SUN is not truly known, as may be ſeen by comparing <hi>Aſtronomical Tables,</hi> even of the beſt and lateſt Authors, <hi>Kep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Wing, Bullialdus, Shackerly,</hi> &amp;c. Alas it is not the work of a <hi>private Hand,</hi> or <hi>Head,</hi> that can conquer this HYDRA: It becomes the tremend Pains and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of a <hi>General Council,</hi> with an EMPEROUR or RING preſent at it, and in the <hi>Head</hi> of it, thereby the better to give Encouragement to ſo <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Glorious</hi> a <hi>Work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as in thoſe of <hi>Nice,</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61670:23"/>
               <hi>Chalccdon.</hi> In the later of which, when they came to an accord about this <hi>Holy Feaſt,</hi> they all with one Voice made this Pious Acclamation, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Paſcha in Orbi Terrarum!</hi> There is but ONE EASTER now all the World over.</p>
            <p>What hath been, may be, and we have the ſame <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> to rely on: The ſame <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>genuity</hi> to aſſiſt us: We want only the ſame <hi>Induſtry,</hi> (and I was about to ſay the ſame <hi>Encouragement,</hi>) with them that have gone before us.</p>
            <p>Let us obſerve further, That this <hi>Holy Feaſt</hi> of FASTER, both for its Name and Uſe, of <hi>All Feaſts</hi> ought to be moſt punctually and truly obſerved. Of the <hi>Name</hi> we have ſpoken ſomewhat before, and ſomething likewiſe of its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> But it may moreover be remembred, that the HOLY CHURCH, for the advantage of all <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ians,</hi> hath appointed it to be obſerved as a time of PACIFICATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, when to bring our <hi>Peace Offerings</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and to <hi>One Another.</hi> And it is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61670:23"/>therefore juſtly ſtiled <hi>FEST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M PACIS;</hi> the bleſſed Feaſt of Peace; becauſe at this time the Sun of Righteouſneſs, and PRINCE of PEACE, aroſe from the <hi>Grave,</hi> (according to what was Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied long before of him,) to bring PEACE and <hi>Salvation</hi> to all Men. And how requiſite it is to have a FEAST of ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a <hi>Memorandum,</hi> and Immenſe <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> to the World, truly Stated and Obſerved, I ſubmit to the Judgement of all <hi>Wiſe Men,</hi> and good <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I well remember what a great Buſtle, <hi>Anno</hi> 1664, there was in this <hi>Nation,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the right obſerving of this HOLY FEAST. The KING and COUNCH were troubled with complaints about it. And it was alledged to the <hi>Kings Majeſty.</hi> that all the <hi>Almanack-makers</hi> for that year were <hi>miſtaken</hi> in the right timing of this FEAST, and had impoſed a wrong EA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER upon the World. Upon which noiſy Charge, the Learned Dr. <hi>PELL.</hi> Chaplain to the (then) Arch-Biſhop of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61670:24"/>
               <hi>Canterbury,</hi> wrote an Ingenious Diſcourſe in a Letter to a Friend in <hi>London,</hi> which was afterwards Printed, bearing this <hi>Title,</hi> EASTER <hi>not</hi> MISTIMED. In which, this worthy Gentleman, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved where the <hi>Errour</hi>-lay, and the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> or <hi>Almanack-makers</hi> were alſo juſtly defended, as well in reſpect of the <hi>Truth</hi> of their <hi>Art,</hi> as from an impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their confederating together, to delude the World with a <hi>Falſe Eaſter,</hi> whereas many of them lived remote from <hi>London,</hi> and from each other, and the moſt of them unknown One to the Other. And the next year, <hi>viz.</hi> 1665. ſeveral of them that wrote Almanacks, as Mr. <hi>WHARTON,</hi> M. <hi>WING,</hi> Mr. <hi>BOOKER,</hi> and my SELF, as ſenſible of the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as well as Unreaſonableneſs of that ridiculous CLAMOUR, wrote a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Defence of the ART, as to that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the ſeveral ALMANACKS of that year, as may be ſeen by any that pleaſe to take the pains to peruſe them.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61670:24"/>
            <p>But now, that we may not only talk of ERRORS, but teach how to ſet them Strait and Even, let me here humbly and faithfully endeavour to ſhew how they may be amended.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to keep <hi>EASTER</hi> truly for Ever.</head>
               <p>In my purſuit of this <hi>Excellent</hi> VERI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY, I have found out <hi>Two</hi> very <hi>Eaſie Ways,</hi> whereby to accompliſh this <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous End;</hi> (Nay, they are in ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the ſame, though ſeemingly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.) as proceeding from <hi>Two very Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men,</hi> and <hi>Excellent Aſtronomers,</hi> even of our own Age. Which proves that the <hi>Scientifical Genius</hi> of this <hi>Intelligent Nation</hi> is not at REST until it have not only <hi>diſcover'd,</hi> but <hi>done</hi> ſomething of SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VICE to ſo great and glorious a <hi>Truth,</hi> as is the right Eſtabliſhment of this HOLY FEAST.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The firſt way I have met with for Eſtabliſhing the right obſervation of this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61670:25"/>HOLY FEAST, that it may no more be liable to <hi>Errour,</hi> is from the Works of that late Learned Gentleman, Sir <hi>GEORGE WHARTON,</hi> Baronet.</p>
               <p>But before I diſcover the way, give me leave, from the ſame Author, to ſhew you what great <hi>Errours</hi> will occur, in caſe the CALENDAR be not corrected, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>Without a Correction of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> EASTER DAY will fall a week diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Time aſſign'd by the <hi>Rule</hi> in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> as it hath happen'd ſince the Year of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1600. <hi>Twenty Times,</hi> to <hi>Anno</hi> 1664. <hi>viz.</hi> In the Years 1602. 1609. 1610. 1613. 1616. 1619. 1620. 1623. 1626. 1630. 1637. 1640. 1643. 1646. 1647. 1650. 1653. 1657. 1661. 1664 And will ſo again, (ſays this worthy <hi>Author</hi>) unleſs a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> be obtain'd,) in the Years 1667. 1669. 1673. 1677. 1681. 1684 1685. 1687. 1688. 1691. 1694. 1697. And <hi>Thirty One times more</hi> before the Year 1800.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61670:25"/>
                  <p>Nor is this all: For there oft-times happens a whole <hi>Monthy Errour,</hi> as to the time of the Celebration thereof, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already fallen out ſo <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſince that of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> viz.</hi> in the years 1625. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and ſo will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, (without a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi>) in the years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1723. 174<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1750. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and in the year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>07. For in thoſe years there will happen (from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>) two <hi>Full Moons</hi> before our EASTER can be kept.</p>
                  <p>Nay, there falls out very often no leſs than 35. days, (or <hi>span<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROUR, in the time of our EASTER, having already fallen out ſo no leſs than <hi>Eleven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſince the year <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> viz.</hi> in the years, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1622. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1663. and ſo will again, (without an <hi>amendment</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>) in the years, 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> And juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> more before the year 1800.</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61670:26"/>
                  <p>But, in the years 2437. 2467. 2491. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there will be 42 days ERROUR, and ſome time afterward no leſs than 49 days: And after the year 2698. (if the old <hi>Cale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dar</hi> ſhould be ſtill retain'd) it will <hi>Never again happen according to the Rule of the Church:</hi> which fixes it on the <hi>Sunday</hi> following the firſt <hi>Full Moon</hi> next after the VERNAL AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOS. <hi>Vid. Calend. Carol. pro An.</hi> 1665.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Now, let us conſider the way he teaches to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and prevent theſe ERROURS for time to come; And that is this, <hi>viz.</hi> —That if all the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> were <hi>omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> for <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that alone would gradually, and inſenſibly, without the leaſt inconveniency, bring us <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> before the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ACCOUNT, and be exactly agreeable to the SUNS place at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOUR. Whereas the very <hi>GREGO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (though now the Beſt and the Trueſt) would be <hi>Two
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61670:26"/>day leſs Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> That being only reduced to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, if after this, the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> be kept as before (except every 132. years, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>EAF-DAY muſt be omitted for ever,) or elſe, that <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Day</hi> be ſtruck off every 100 years (except in each 400.) for ever; there would need no more to have our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (and all other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in depending) kept according to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Obſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Demonſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p>For by ſuppoſing the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Year to be (after <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>) 365 Days, 5 Hours, 49 Minutes, 4 Seconds, 21 Thirds, the <hi>Annual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> allowed it by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>AR,</hi> will be 10 Minutes, 55 Seconds, 39 Thirds, which <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in 132 Years; and but 2 Minutes, 25 Seconds, 48 Thirds, over. And 3 Days in 400 Years, with 51 Minutes over;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61670:27"/>which makes but One Day in 11294 Years, very <hi>inconſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Oh! that our <hi>Britiſh Nation,</hi> (as Polite in <hi>Arts,</hi> &amp;c. as any other <hi>Countrey</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> or perhaps in the whole World.) might be but ſo happy as to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Glory of a right <hi>Correction</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ALENDAR, even for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ASTER's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>AKE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> moſt <hi>Sacred,</hi> as being of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; and ever in uſe among <hi>Chriſtine</hi> ſince the <hi>Glorinas Reſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and SAY<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>DUR.</p>
                  <p>The Good and <hi>Pio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Emperour, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTINE</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> termed it, and that truly, <hi>The moſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>of</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>EASTS. Even that <hi>CONSTANTINE</hi> which firſt gave <hi>Wings</hi> to CHRISTIANITY; who after his having <hi>Embraced</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Ever BLESSED JESUS, moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily and happily <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> it by a LAW.</p>
                  <p>True it is, there hath been (as before was remembred,) many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the EASTERN and WESTERN
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61670:27"/>
                     <hi>Churches,</hi> about the right <hi>Obſervation</hi> of this HOLY FEAST, and ſeveral <hi>Councils</hi> conven'd about it, who have endeavour'd to ſet it right. But I ſay, (with that moſt Learned and Excellent Prelate, BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHOP <hi>ANDREWS,</hi>) they met, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the FEAST it ſelf, (for that was <hi>never diſputed</hi> by <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) but about the true time of its Celebration only. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>AST<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> himſelf, (though guilty of <hi>Hereſie</hi> in the buſineſs of this great STIVA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,) never denied an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but queſtion'd the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of its <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>tion.</hi> As indeed any Man may reaſonably do, (provided he do not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> affront <hi>Authority</hi>) conſidering the many <hi>Errours</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> which have been broach'd about it; and never fear being Branded as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for ſo doing.</p>
                  <p>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> was the firſt Man that ſtarted the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO-DEC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that held it unlawful to keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but upon the <hi>Fourteenth Day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (whence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61670:28"/>it was denominated,) which was agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the obſervation of the <hi>Jemiſh Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ver:</hi> A <hi>Prail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> no way comporting with the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> or of our Bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reſurrection.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="2">II. To return from what I digreſſed: Becauſe I am enter'd upon ſo Excellent and <hi>Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (fit for the Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a more Learned and Worthy Pen, I confeſs.) I will omit nothing that may be neceſſary for the Correction, and right keeping of this SACRED FEAST. I will therefore ſubjoyn another <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>nſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the CALENDAR. Which, (that I may not incur the hateful Cenſure of a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>) I do own to have found Printed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (imperfectly) with a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the MOVEABLE FEA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>TS for 532 years to come, from that time; Calculated by ſome <hi>Curions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Hand,</hi> to me wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. I wiſh I knew the Induſtrious and Laborious <hi>Author</hi> thereof, that I
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61670:28"/>might, <hi>(Nomine,)</hi> pay him his much merited reſpect. For had I been acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with that his <hi>worthy Work</hi> ſooner, it had ſaved me a vaſt deal of Pains in the compiling of my EASTER TABLE for more than 200 years to come, from <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1677. (an Abſtract whereof I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Inſerted.) Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I performed at the Command of the Honourable <hi>GEORGE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Eſquire,</hi> my moſt <hi>Noble</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſince deceaſed.—'Tis this.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> toward the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>dar.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The quantity of the <hi>Solar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear</hi> is ſaid to conſiſt of 365 Days, 5 Hours, 49 Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, 16 Seconds. Others will have it to be two or three Seconds more. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive two or three Seconds in this caſe makes an <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Variation.</hi> I ſhall therefore adhere to the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That the quantity of the true <hi>Solar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear</hi> is,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61670:29"/>365 Days, 5 Hours, 49 Minutes, 16 Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">h.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">ſe.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>23</cell>
                           <cell>17</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The odd 5 ho. 49. min. 16. ſec. in 4 years, (as in the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,</hi>) makes but 23 h. 17 m. ſe. 4</item>
                     <item>Which 23 h. 17. m. 4 ſe. is leſs than a whole day, by 00 h. 42 m. 56 ſe.</item>
                     <item>So that the making of the <hi>Fourth Tear</hi> to conſiſt of 366 Days, (which we call <hi>Leap-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ear</hi>) doth thruſt back the VERNAL AEQU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>NOX the quantity of — 00 h. 42 m. 56 ſe.</item>
                     <item>And if there ſhould be no <hi>Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>alation</hi> of <hi>One Day</hi> in <hi>Four Years,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Fourth Year</hi> ſhould conſiſt but of 365 Days; then will the VERNAL AEQUINOX be thruſt forward in Four years, the quantity of— 23 h. 17 m. 04 ſe.</item>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:61670:29"/>
                     <item>In 1664. (the Number of Years Elapſed from the <hi>Birth</hi> of our SAVIOUR, and the <hi>particular Year</hi> which the AUTHOR made uſe of,) are contained 4, 6 <hi>Leap-Years;</hi> which 416 being multiplied by 42 m. 56 ſec. do make 12 days, 9 hours, 40. min. 16. ſec. ſo that by the obſervation of 416 <hi>Leap-Yers</hi> together, without the omiſſion of any one, the AEQUINOXES are <hi>thruſe back</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1664. the quantity of— 12 d. 9 h. 40 m. 16 ſe.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And if the CALENDAR continue without <hi>Reformation</hi> for the ſpace of 1664 Years more, the VERNAL AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOX will be in <hi>February</hi> For the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> whereof, I offer this Expedient.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61670:30"/>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>To <hi>Reduce</hi> the <hi>VERNAL AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOX</hi> to the ſame Day upon which it was at the <hi>Birth</hi> of <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Let <hi>Thirteen Leap-Year.</hi> be omitted; that is, let the <hi>Year</hi> conſiſt but of 365 <hi>Days,</hi> for <hi>Fiſty two Years</hi> following the Year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>004, and the VERNAL AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOX will inſenſibly return on the <hi>ſame day</hi> it was at the <hi>Birth</hi> of CHRIST.</p>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <head>See the <hi>Demonſtration</hi>
                           </head>
                           <row>
                              <cell role="label">d.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">h.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">ſe.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>17</cell>
                              <cell>04</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                              <cell>14</cell>
                              <cell>41</cell>
                              <cell>52</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>It appeareth above, that the <hi>omiſion</hi> of one <hi>LEAP-YEARS</hi> doth put forward the <hi>AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOX,</hi> the quantity of 23 h. 17 m. 4 ſec. and therefore the <hi>omiſſion</hi> of 13 LEAP-YEARS toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do make 12 days, 14 hours, 41 minutes, 52 ſeconds, (as in the Margin,) ſo that the <hi>omiſſion</hi> of 13 LEAP-YEARS together, will make the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>QUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ES to run <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the quantity of 12 d. 15 h. 51 m. 52 ſe.</item>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:61670:30"/>
                        <item>It appeareth alſo above, That <hi>Anno</hi> 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, the VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAL AEQUINOX was run <hi>back</hi> the quantity of— 12 d. 9 h. 40 m. 16 ſe.</item>
                        <item>So that ſubſtracting 12 d. 9 h. 40 m. 16 ſe. (the <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> which the AEQUINOX was run <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> Anno, 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.) from 12 d. 14 h. 41 m. 52 ſe. the <hi>quantity</hi> which the <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of 13 LEAP-YEARS will thruſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the AEQUINOX, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1716, the remainder is, 5 h. 1 m. 36 ſe. By which it plainly appears, that if 13 LEAPYEARS be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (as is before expreſſed) the AEQUINOX, <hi>Anno.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>16, will be <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> but only the quantity of— 00 d. 5 h. 13 m. 6 ſe.</item>
                        <item>The AEQUINOXS being thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> (or by what <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> it ſhall pleaſe His <hi>Gracious Majeſty</hi> to cauſe it to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61670:31"/>it being <hi>once done,</hi> 
                           <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> may be kept from <hi>running Back,</hi> or <hi>Forward,</hi> the quantity of Twenty four Hours for <hi>Ever,</hi> after this manner, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>To keep the <hi>AEQUINOXES</hi> from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Let every 34th. LEAP-TEAR be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the <hi>Anticipation</hi> will not be the <hi>quantity</hi> of <hi>word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> in 10000 <hi>Years.</hi> The <hi>Demonſtration</hi> whereof followeth.</p>
                     <p>It is before <hi>Demonſtrated,</hi> That the <hi>keeping</hi> of ONE LEAP-YEAR doth put <hi>back</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>NOXES 42 min. 56 ſec. and therefore the <hi>keeping</hi> of 33 LEAP-YEARS together, doth put them <hi>bark</hi> the quantity of— 23 h. 36 m. 48 ſe.</p>
                     <p>Alſo by <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of One LEAP-YEAR, (as is before expreſſed,) they are <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> — 23 h. 17 m. 04 ſe.</p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:61670:31"/>
                     <p>The <hi>Difference,</hi> or <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation</hi> therefore in 136 Years, is but— 00 h. 19 m. 44 ſe.</p>
                     <p>So that it is <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> That if from <hi>reducing</hi> the AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOX, <hi>viz. An. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> three</hi> LEAP-YEARS be <hi>kept,</hi> and the 34th. <hi>viz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> be <hi>omitted,</hi> the going <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> of the AEQUINOXES in every 136 years, will be but 19 m. 44 ſec. And taking the 19 min. 44 ſec. (the <hi>quantity</hi> run <hi>back</hi> from the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> to the <hi>year</hi> 1852.) from 5 ho. 1 min. 36 ſec. (the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> it was <hi>too forward Anno</hi> 1716.) the remainder that the AEQUINOXES will be <hi>too forward, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> will be the <hi>quantity</hi> of— 04 h. 41 m. 52 ſe.</p>
                     <p>So that it will be above <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> before the AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOXES will be put <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61670:32"/>ONE MINUTE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> And in 9000 <hi>Years</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, if every 34th. LEAP-YEAR be <hi>omitted,</hi> (as aforeſaid,) the <hi>Anticipation</hi> will not be the <hi>quantity</hi> of <hi>Twenty four Hours,</hi> and may then (by the <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of another LEAP-YEAR more,) be <hi>Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> Thus far this ENCELLENT AU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOR.</p>
                     <p>Now, how requiſite it is that AUTHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITY be humbly put in <hi>mind</hi> of a <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſo <hi>Auguſt</hi> and <hi>Weighty,</hi> as is the right Obſervation of the HOLY FEAST of our <hi>Bleſsed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>'s Reſurrection,</hi> will, I hope, moſt fully appear from the <hi>ſoregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>urſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> as alſo by divers <hi>pre-viſional Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</hi> For without a <hi>Correction</hi> of the CALENDAR, we ſhall be <hi>Obnoxious</hi> to many ERRORS, and moſt certainly find,</p>
                     <p n="1">I. That within the compaſs of a very <hi>ſmall Circuit</hi> of <hi>Years, viz.</hi> from this very <hi>Year</hi> of 1687, to the <hi>Year</hi> 1702 (A <hi>ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ime</hi> only) we ſhall be <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> of no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61670:32"/>leſs than <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ight</hi> or <hi>Nine</hi> apparent ER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROURS in reſpect of the right <hi>Timing</hi> of the <hi>Holy. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſt</hi> of EASTER. Almoſt as many ERROURS as <hi>Years.</hi> Not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what more will certainly be found after that <hi>Year;</hi> which will, (indeed) be <hi>very Numerous.</hi> As before you have plainly been inform'd.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. In Tract of Time, if no <hi>Correction</hi> be obtain'd, the very <hi>Seaſon</hi> of the <hi>Year</hi> will be <hi>vary'd</hi> ſo much, that our WIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER will be found at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>D-SUMMER; and our <hi>Sum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> or <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Days.</hi> will appear at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>: and our BLESSED <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and the BAPTIST be forced to Exchange their TROPICKS. as before you have heard.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, (though in it ſelf not abſolutely <hi>true,</hi>) will, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed already it frequently doth,) carry the GARLAND from the <hi>Julian Account,</hi> and <hi>make it</hi> to be look'd on as a <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>anger</hi> to TRUTH</p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:61670:33"/>
                     <p n="4">IV. If no <hi>Correction</hi> of our CALEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAR be made, we ſhall be commonly conſtrain'd to the <hi>Keeping</hi> of <hi>Two EA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERS</hi> in <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e Year,</hi> or within the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs</hi> of leſs than 365 <hi>Days.</hi> As it fell out <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 1668, and muſt again the <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xt Year</hi> 1688, and very often afterwards.</p>
                     <p n="5">V. Without a <hi>Correction</hi> of the CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENDAR, our Learned'ſt <hi>Divines,</hi> and <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſtorians,</hi> as well as <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hematicians,</hi> will be at a <hi>Loſs,</hi> in the right aſſigning of EA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER, and ſtand <hi>liable</hi> to be <hi>Taxed,</hi> or <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ed</hi> with IGNORANCE in the juſt, and proper LIMITS of this <hi>Sacred Feaſt;</hi> as the Learned and Noble <hi>BARONI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> once was, by the Induſtrious <hi>Sethus Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſius,</hi> that Excellent <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">VI. For want of an <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mendation</hi> of the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> CALENDAR, our CHURCH and STATE in <hi>Time</hi> will be compell'd to the <hi>like Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ble,</hi> as once was the good <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, viz.</hi> To ſend their <hi>Paſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> into all. Parts of His <hi>Majeſty'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="57" facs="tcp:61670:33"/>Dominions</hi> to give <hi>Warning</hi> for the <hi>right Obſervation</hi> of EASTER. which muſt prove a very great trouble.</p>
                     <p>But the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of theſe things, and of many <hi>other Conſequences,</hi> (not readily foreſeen,) hence ariſing, I moſt <hi>humbly ſubmit</hi> to the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of thoſe in AUTHORITY over us, in CHURCH and STATE, who are (if GOD ſo pleaſe,) able, not only to <hi>Compaſs,</hi> but <hi>Command</hi> ſo great and <hi>needful,</hi> as well as <hi>uſeful</hi> a CORRECTION of the CALENDAR, which we at <hi>this Day,</hi> by <hi>Authority,</hi> muſt, and do <hi>follow,</hi> though in it ſelf very <hi>Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> and <hi>Defective.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>According to this <hi>Eſſay,</hi> for an <hi>Emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of the CALENDAR, I will here inſert a TABLE for the <hi>true</hi> finding out the <hi>Dominical Letter,</hi> and EASTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAY, (upon which all the other <hi>Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Feaſts</hi> depend,) for <hi>Two hundred Tears</hi> yet to come: Which if <hi>Authority</hi> ſhall vouchſafe to <hi>Approve</hi> of, and <hi>Countenance,</hi> may be <hi>continued</hi> for <hi>Ever.</hi> 'Tis this which follows.</p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:61670:34"/>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell role="label">Anno Chriſt.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">Dom. Letter</cell>
                              <cell role="label">EASTER DAY</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1665
<note place="margin">
                                    <hi>The Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen</hi> Leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>years <hi>omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the former Rule.</hi>
                                 </note>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1666</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1667</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1668</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1669</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1670</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1671</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1672</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1673</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1674</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1675</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1676</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1677</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1678</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1679</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1680</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1681</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1682</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1683</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1684</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1685</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1686</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1687</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1688</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1689</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1690</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1691</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1692</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1693</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1694</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1695</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1696</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1697</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1698</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1699</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>10</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1700</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1701</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1702</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1703</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1704</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1705</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1706</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1707</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1708</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1709</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1710</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1711</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1712</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1713</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1714</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1715</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1716</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1717</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1718</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1719</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1720</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <note n="*" place="margin">Leap-years <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd as before.</hi>
                                 </note> B A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1721</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1722</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1723</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1724</cell>
                              <cell>D C</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1725</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1726</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1727</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1728</cell>
                              <cell>F E</cell>
                              <cell>20</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1729</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1730</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1731</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1732</cell>
                              <cell>A G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1733</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1734</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1735</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1736</cell>
                              <cell>C B</cell>
                              <cell>24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1737</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1738</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <pb n="59" facs="tcp:61670:34"/>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1739</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 21</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1740</cell>
                              <cell>E D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1741</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1742</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1743</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1744</cell>
                              <cell>G <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1745</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1746</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1747</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>18</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1748</cell>
                              <cell>B A</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1749</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1750</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1751</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1752</cell>
                              <cell>D C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1753</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1754</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1755</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1756</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1757</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1758</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1759</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>10</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1760</cell>
                              <cell>A C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1761</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1762</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1763</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1764</cell>
                              <cell>C <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 10</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1765</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1766</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1767</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1768</cell>
                              <cell>E D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1769</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1770</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1771</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1772</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1773</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1774</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1775</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1776</cell>
                              <cell>B <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1777</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1778</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1779</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1780</cell>
                              <cell>D C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 18</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1781</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1782</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 26</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1783</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1784</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1785</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1786</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1787</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1788</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1789</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1790</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1791</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1792</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1793</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1794</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1795</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1796</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1797</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1798</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1799</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1800</cell>
                              <cell>G F</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1801</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1802</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1803</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1804</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1805</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1806</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1807</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 20</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1808</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1809</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1810</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1811</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1812</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>20</cell>
                           </row>
                           <pb n="60" facs="tcp:61670:35"/>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1813</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1814</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1815</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1816</cell>
                              <cell>A G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1817</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1818</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1819</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1820</cell>
                              <cell>C B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1821</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>8822</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1823</cell>
                              <cell>F <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>21</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1824</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> D</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1825</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1826</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1827</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1828</cell>
                              <cell>G <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1829</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1830</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1831</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1832</cell>
                              <cell>B <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1833</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1834</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>21</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1835</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1836</cell>
                              <cell>D C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1837</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1838</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1839</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1840</cell>
                              <cell>F E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1841</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1842</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>18</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1843</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>10</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1844</cell>
                              <cell>A G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1845</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1846</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1847</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 29</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1848</cell>
                              <cell>C <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1849</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1850</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>22</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1851</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 14</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1852</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <note n="*" place="margin">
                                    <hi>The</hi> Leap year <hi>omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the former Rule.</hi>
                                 </note> E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 30</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1853</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1854</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1855</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1856</cell>
                              <cell>A G</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 15</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1857</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1858</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1859</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1860</cell>
                              <cell>C B</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1861</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1862</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1863</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1864</cell>
                              <cell>E D</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 19</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1865</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1866</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1867</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1868</cell>
                              <cell>G F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1869</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1870</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1871</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1872</cell>
                              <cell>R A</cell>
                              <cell>16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1873</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1874</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 31</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1875</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1876</cell>
                              <cell>D C</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1877</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 27</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1878</cell>
                              <cell>A</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1879</cell>
                              <cell>G</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1880</cell>
                              <cell>F E</cell>
                              <cell>20</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1881</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1882</cell>
                              <cell>C</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 28</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1883</cell>
                              <cell>B</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 17</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1884</cell>
                              <cell>A G</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1885</cell>
                              <cell>F</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1886</cell>
                              <cell>E</cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 13</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1887</cell>
                              <cell>D</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1888</cell>
                              <cell>C <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>24</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:61670:35"/>
                     <p>Now if <hi>Authority</hi> ſhall think fit to <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> hereof, the ſame GOLDEN-NUM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BER, AEPACT, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may ſtill be <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> as is in <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> with Us at the <hi>preſent,</hi> and no other <hi>Alteration</hi> required in <hi>Either,</hi> than what is found by this NEW TABLE, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of 13 LEAP-YEARS, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>former Rule.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let not any <hi>Ingenious Artiſt,</hi> or others <hi>wonder</hi> that this <hi>New Table</hi> differs from the common EASTER TABLES, or our preſent <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> or the ordinary <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods</hi> for the finding the <hi>Time</hi> of this HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY FEAST; for ſo it muſt needs do, ſince the LEAP-YEARS for 52 Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether are <hi>omitted,</hi> according to this <hi>New Hypotheſis</hi> for the <hi>Correcting</hi> of the preſent ERROURS attending it. By reaſon whereof this HOLY FEAST, will ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, (ſeemingly,) fall upon <hi>different Days,</hi> not only of the <hi>Monch,</hi> but <hi>Week,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>preſent Eſtabliſhment.</hi> And ſo it will continue to do until <hi>Anno</hi> 1852. In which <hi>Year</hi> the LEAP-DAY,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61670:36"/>(according to the <hi>former Rule,</hi>) again will be <hi>omitted,</hi> as you may ſee by the TABLE. After which time the GOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEN-NUMBER, and <hi>Dominital Letter,</hi> (as the <hi>Table</hi> exhibits to your view,) will come into the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Order</hi> they were, as in <hi>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er Years,</hi> or as they <hi>are</hi> at the <hi>preſent.</hi> And then alſo the LEAP-YEARS will keep their <hi>right Courſes,</hi> as <hi>now,</hi> (except before excepted,) for <hi>many Ages</hi> to come, and be ſubject to no <hi>Errour</hi> at all.</p>
                     <p>To conclude, I have before mention'd <hi>One</hi> grand occaſion of <hi>Errours</hi> happening in the <hi>Time</hi> of this HOLY FEAST to be the <hi>Preceſsion</hi> of the VERNAL AEQUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOX, which from the firſt <hi>Council of Nice,</hi> to our <hi>Times,</hi> hath <hi>Anticipated</hi> not fewer than <hi>Eleven Days.</hi> It falling <hi>now</hi> on, or about the 10th <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>March;</hi> whereas at the time of that <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>uncil,</hi> it was on the 21ſt. <hi>Day</hi> of the ſame <hi>Month,</hi> &amp;c. But there is another <hi>Ground</hi> alſo of this <hi>Errour,</hi> (which I mention'd not before,) <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Lunations</hi> or <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> of the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:61670:36"/>which by reaſon of the too great <hi>quantity</hi> allowed them, do, in every 19 Years <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate</hi> almoſt <hi>an Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> and an <hi>Half;</hi> and in 132 Years and an half, <hi>One whole Day:</hi> And therefore not <hi>Exactly</hi> to be found by the <hi>Golden-Number,</hi> although on thoſe <hi>Lunations</hi> the <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ASTER depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, as of It all the reſt of the <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eable Feasts.</hi> Now both theſe together were the <hi>juſt occaſion</hi> of the <hi>Roman Emendation,</hi> whereby that CHURCH doth always produce EASTER on the <hi>Sunday</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the firſt FULL MOON next after the VERNAL AEQ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>INOX</hi> agreeable to the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> and alſo to the <hi>Rule</hi> for finding thereof in our <hi>Engliſh Common-Prayer-Book,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>—When He is come—He will lead you into All Truth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <bibl>Joh. cap. 26. v. 13.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 3. line 13. read <hi>MONAT.</hi> p. 5. l. 11. r. <hi>Right hand.</hi> p. 10. l. antepenult. r. 31 <hi>April</hi> 2.4.5. p. 29. l. 2. r. <hi>as I find.</hi> p. 50. l. 19. in the Margin, r. 12 <hi>d.</hi> 14 <hi>h.</hi> 41 <hi>m.</hi> 52 <hi>ſe.</hi> p. 51. l. 13. in the Margin, r. 5. <hi>h.</hi> 1 <hi>m.</hi> 36 <hi>ſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:61670:37"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IF the <hi>Reader</hi> prove ſo <hi>Christianly</hi> kind, as to <hi>Correct</hi> the ERRORS of the <hi>Preſs</hi> and <hi>Author.</hi> I have little to Apologize for: Excepting what may poſſibly be <hi>Objected</hi> by ſome TENDER STOMACHS, about its being <hi>Printed</hi> with <hi>Red Letters.</hi>—To ſatisfie the <hi>Soruple</hi> of ſuch, I aſſure them, (1.) It was no SUPERSTITIOUS <hi>conceit</hi> led me thereto, but as I diſcourſe of the MOST HOLY of <hi>All</hi> CHRISTIAN FEASTS, ſo I had a deſire it ſhould be <hi>Printed</hi> ſomewhat <hi>Semblable</hi> to the HOLY RUBRICK, it being the moſt GLORIOUS FEASTIVAL therein. (2.) I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to advance the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LISH IMPRIMARY,</hi> and to ſhew the <hi>Learned</hi> of our <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> and <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> That <hi>Common-Prayer-Books, Miſſals, Breviaries, Manuels,</hi> &amp;c. may be as <hi>Nobly</hi> and <hi>Gracefully</hi> PRINTED in <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> as in any other part of the <hi>World.</hi> 'Tis hoped therefore that the <hi>Printing</hi> thereof <hi>thus,</hi> may paſs without any <hi>Siniſter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> or <hi>Cenſure</hi> of Any.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61670:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
